Estabrook, Arthur H.; Papers apap069
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Arthur H. Estabrook Papers
1908-1962
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap069
2.0 cubic ft.
Papers of eugenics researcher Arthur Estabrook focus on racial integrity, sterilization of the mentally defective, venereal disease, intelligence, and criminality. Limited material is availible on the Jukes of New York state, the "Tribe of Ishmael" of Indiana, and the Carrie Buck trial.
Biographical Sketch
Dr. Arthur Howard Estabrook was born on May 9, 1885, to Arthur Francis and Susan Rebecca (Breck) in Leicester, Massachusetts. Estabrook earned an AB degree in 1905 and an AM in 1906 from Clark College in Worcester, Massachusetts. He was a fellow and assistant in zoology at Clark in 1906-1907. Estabrook received his PhD from Johns Hopkins in 1910 and was a student at the School of Philanthropy in New York in 1914. Estabrook married Jessie McCubbin on October 25, 1911, and married Anne Ruth Medcalf on July 8, 1931, after his first wife's death.
Dr. Estabrook worked in the Eugenics Record Office of Carnegie Institution of Washington (1910-1929) and served as a special investigator for the Indiana State Commission on Mental Defectives (1916-1918). Estabrook traveled to Virginia on behalf of the Eugenics Record Office to study the issues and people involved in the Virginia sterilization case of Carrie Buck. Estabrook served in the U.S. Army in 1918-1920 as a Captain in the Sanitary Corps. He began working for the American Society for the Control of Cancer in 1929 and served as president of the Eugenics Research Association in 1925-1926. [Unless otherwise noted all information in this text is from Who's Who in America, 1935-1936 edition (Chicago: Marquis Who's Who)].
Estabrook died on December 6, 1973, in Chatham Center, New York [Files of the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, Chatham (NY) Courier, 13 December 1973].
Scope and Contents
The papers of Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook contain correspondence, news clippings, research materials, and reports and publications on his research on racial integrity, sterilization of the mentally defective, venereal disease campaign in New York City, crippled children in Buffalo and Erie County, and a housing study in Buffalo.
The major part of the collection deals with studies on racial integrity; mixtures of Indians, Whites, and African Americans; intelligence and criminality. This early eugenics work by Estabrook was conducted in Pembroke, North Carolina, and in Robeson County, North Carolina. The resultant publication, co-authored with Ivan, E. McDougle, was Mongrel Virginians: The Win Tribe, published in 1926.
The collection contains some background material for the 1915 study of the Jukes of New York state, and the 1922 study of the "Tribe of Ishmael" of Indiana. The material dealing with the Carrie Buck trial (the 1924 case against the Virginia statute on sterilization of the mentally defective, which was eventually upheld by the U.S. Supreme Court in Buck v. Bell [1927]) consists of limited correspondence, news clippings, and court records. Two studies resulted in publications: "The Crippled Children Situation in Buffalo and Erie County" and A Roof Over Their Heads. What's What in Housing in Buffalo.
In addition to the writings by Estabrook, the collection is of interest because of the newspaper clippings showing current attitudes and the wide range of the research materials included.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into 14 series.
Series 1: Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Families in Pembroke, North Carolina and Robeson Counties, North Carolina, by Estabrook and Ivan E. McDougle, 1916-1917, 1923-1927
Series 2: Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his Studies of Racial Characteristics, 1922, 1924, 1926, undated
Series 3: Manuscripts by Others, 1924-1925
Series 4: Genealogical Charts, undated
Series 5: Notes, 1908-1925, undated
Series 6: Photographs, 1923-1925, 1931, undated
Series 7: Clippings, 1912-1936, undated
Series 8: Miscellaneous Publications by Others, 1914, 1917, 1922, 1924-1926
Series 9: Carrie Buck Trial, 1924-1927
Series 10: Venereal Disease Campaign, 1924-1925, 1929-1930, 1936, undated
Series 11: Crippled Children in Buffalo and Erie County, 1936, 1943, 1947
Series 12: Housing Study, Buffalo, 1930, 1943, undated
Series 13: Publications by Estabrook, 1912, 1920, 1923, 1926
Series 14: Research Material, 1908-1962
Series 1-8 relate to studies on racial integrity, mixtures of Indians, Whites, and African Americans, intelligence and criminality. This early work by Estabrook was conducted in Pembroke, North Carolina, and in Robeson County, North Carolina. Please note the dates for series 5 and 7 are not inclusive.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook. The first accession was received in March 1966 and additional material was deposited in 1968.
Related Materials
An image of Carrie and Emma Buck from the collection as well as other information about Estabrook is available from the Image Archive on the American Eugenics Movement.
The Carnegie Institution's holdings include correspondence of Estabrook for the period 1926-1929. The correspondence is described as six items including letters about Estabrook's annuity policy, where to send a package, and two letters discussing his publication Mongrel Virginians. Contact information for the Carnegie Insitution is availabe at http://carnegieinstitution.org/reading_room.html.
The G. Stanley Hall Papers held at the Clark University Archives and Special Collections include Estabrook correspondence in the Graduate Student Correspondence (undated) and President Papers (1902-1914) series.
The records of the American Eugenics Society at the American Philosophical Society also include undated Estabrook correspondence.
Access
The collection is open to use by "qualified and responsible scholars". Please note that several files are restricted and this is noted next to the respective folder. Researchers must complete a non-disclosure form before gaining access and reproductions are not permitted.
Medicine and Health Care; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Involuntary sterilization -- Virginia.; Miscegenation; Heredity, Human; Public health; Housing -- New York (State) -- Buffalo; Children with disabilities -- New York (State) -- Buffalo; Public welfare; Sociology; Eugenics; Sexually transmitted diseases; Estabrook, Arthur H. (Arthur Howard), 1885-; Buck, Carrie, 1906-1983.; Juke family
- Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Families in Pembroke, North Carolina and Robeson Counties, North Carolina, by Estabrook and Ivan E. McDougle, 1916-1917; 1923-1927; 1
  - 1916-1917, 1.1 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Familie), Folder 1)
    - a. Claghorn, Kate Holladay, 1916 January 6
      Scope and Contents
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Dr. A. H. Estabrook, Indianapolis, Ind. Typescript, signed 1 l.
    - b. Michael, M. J., 1916 October 23
      Letter, Kingston, N.Y., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Indianapolis, Ind. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - c. Lewis, O. F., 1916 October 26
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Dr. A. H. Estabrook, Indianapolis, Ind. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - d. Hall, Gertrude E., 1917 January 30
      Letter, Utica, N.Y., to Dr. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - e. Evans, Ethel R., 1917 January 31
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Dr. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - f. Evans, Ethel R., 1917 February 14
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Dr. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 2 l.
    - g. [Estabrook], 1917 February 17
      Letter, Indianapolis, Ind., to Miss Ethel R. Evans, New York, N.Y. Carbon of typescript 1 l.
  - 1923, 1.2 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Familie), Folder 2)
    - a. Hubbard, Louisa, 1923 February 1
      Letter, Greenville, N.C. to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Amherst, Va. Typescript and handwritten in ink. 4 p. on 2 l.
    - b. McDougle, Ivan E., 1923 March 8
      Letter, Sweet Briar, Va., to Dr. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - c. McDougle, Ivan E., 1923 April 13
    - d. Wade, Theodora K., 1923 April 14
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Mr. Arthur H. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - e. McDougle, I. E., 1923 April 17
    - f. McDougle, Ivan E., 1923 April 30
    - g. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1923 May 19
      Letter, to Dr. Ivan E. McDougle, Sweet Briar, Va. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - h. McDougle, Ivan E., 1923 September 20
      Letter, Sweet Briar, Va., to Dr. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 2 l.
    - i. [Estabrook], 1923 September 22
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Dr. McDougle. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
  - 1924, 1.3 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Familie), Folder 3)
    - a. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 January 25
    - b. McDougle, Ivan E., 1924 January 27
    - c. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 February 12
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Dr. McDougle. Carbon typescript. 1 l.
    - d. [Estabrook], 1924 February 12
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Min. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - e. Min, 1924 February 15
      Letter, Columbia, S.C., to Arthur. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - f. McDougle, Ivan E., 1924 February 17
    - g. Min, 1924 February 23
      Letter, to Arthur. Typescript with handwritten postscript. 1 l.
    - h. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 March 22
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Miss Harned. Carbon of typescript. 2 l.
    - i. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 March 25
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Dr. Arthur Gray, Richmond, Va. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - j. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 March 26
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Dr. McDougle. Carbon of typescript. 2 l.
    - k. Harned, Eleanor M.
      Letter, [1924?] March 27, to Dr. Estabrook. Handwritten in ink, signed. 5 p. on 3 l.
      Letter, 1924 April 8, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. Estabrook.
    - l. Corbin, A. F.
      Letter, Cold Spring Harbor, Long Island, N.Y. Typed, signed with initials. 1 l.
    - m. Harned, Eleanor M., 1924 April 9
      Letter, Sweet Briar, to Dr. Estabrook. Handwritten in ink, signed. 11 p. on 6 1.
    - n. Rollins, W. E., 1924 April 9
      Note, Alexandria, Va., to Dr. Estabrook. Handwritten in ink, signed. 1 l.
    - o. McDougle, Ivan E., 1924 April 26
    - p. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 May 2
    - q. McDougle, Ivan E., 1924 May 3
      Letter, Sweet Briar, Va., to Dr. Estabrook. Typescript, signed. Enclosure: "Answers to your questions in letter of May 2, 1924". Typescript.2 l.
    - r. (Estabrook], 1924 May 6
    - s. McDougle, Ivan E., 1924 May 7
    - t. McDougle, I. E.
      Memorandum: "Questions May 7, 1924, dated 1924 May 10, Sweet Briar, Va". Typescript. 3 l.
    - u. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 June 23
      Letter, Gitley, Letcher County, Kentucky, to Mr. A. F. Corbin, Pembroke, N.C. Carbon of typescript. 2 l.
    - v. [Estabrook], 1924 July 1
      Memorandum, Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - w. Corbin, A. F., 1924 July 9
      Letter, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. Estabrook. Typescript. 1 l.
    - x. Locklear, A. N., 1924 July 10
      Letter, Pates, N.C., to Mr. Arthur Estabrook, Gitley, Letcher Co., Ky. Handwritten in pencil, signed. 3 l.
    - y. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 July 23
      Letter, Hyden, Ky., to Mr. Corbin. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - z. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 July 24
      Letter, Hyden, Ky., to Mr. A. N. Locklear, Pates, Robeson County, N.C. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - aa. Plecker, W. A., 1924 July 29
      Letter, to Mr. W. N. Clark, Rockbridge Co., Va. Carbon of typescript. 2 l.
    - bb. Corbin, A. F., 1924 August 8
      Letter, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. Estabrook, Hyden, Ky. Typescript with handwritten note in ink. 1 l.
    - cc. Plecker, W. A., 1924 August 11
      Letter, Richmond, VA., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Cold Spring Harbor, Long Island, N.Y. Typescript, signed. 2 l.
    - dd. Plecker, W. A., 1924 August 11
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Dr. Estabrook, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - ee. Plecker, W. A., 1924 August 29
      Letter, to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Cold Spring Harbor, Long Island, N.Y. Typescript, signed. 2 l. 1 carbon of typescript with handwritten note in ink. 2 l.
    - ff. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 September 5
      Letter, Hyden, Ky., to Dr. W. A. Plecker, Richmond, Va. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - gg. Plecker, W. A., 1924 September 9
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Hyden, Ky. Typescript, signed. 2 l.
    - hh. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 September 20
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Dr. Plecker. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - ii. Plecker, W. A., 1924 October 13
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Carnegie Foundation, New York City. Typescript, signed. I halfsheet.
    - jj. Furst, Clyde, 1924 October 14
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Dr. W. A. Plecker, Richmond, Va. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - kk. Plecker, W. A., 1924 October 30
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Philadelphia, Penna. Typescript, signed. I halfsheet.
    - ll. Plecker, W. A., 1924 October 30
      Letter, to Professor Ivan E. McDougle, Baltimore, Md. Carbon of typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - mm. Plecker, W. A., 1924 October 31
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Professor Ivan McDougle, Baltimore, Md. Carbon of typescript, signed. 1 l.
  - 1925, 1.4 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Familie), Folder 4)
    - a. McDougle, Ivan E., 1925 July 5
      Letter, Williamsburg, Va., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Philadelphia, Penna. Typescript, signed. 2 l.
    - b. Plecker, W. A., 1925 September 15
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Dr. A. H. Estabrook, Hyden, Ky. Typescript, signed. 1 l. Enclosure: Plecker, W. A. Letter, 1925 September 15, to Mr. P. S. Beverley, Pera, Amherst Co., Va. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - c. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1925 September 19
      Letter, Hyden, Ky., to Dr. Plecker. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
  - 1926, 1.5 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Familie), Folder 5)
    - a. Burleigh, Louise, 1926 January 22
      Letter, Richmond, Va., to Mr. McDougle. Typescript, with penciled note by McDougle. 1 l.
    - b. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1926 January 23
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Mr. Corbin. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - c. McDougle, 1926 February 9
      Letter, Baltimore, Md., to Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - d. McDougle, 1926 February 10
      Letter, Baltimore, Md., to Estabrook. Typescript, signed, with handwritten note in ink and handwritten note on card attached. 1 l.
    - e. McDougle, I. E., 1926 February 14
    - f. Young, James N., 1926 February 17
      Letter, New York, N.Y., to Mr. Stern, Philadelphia, Pa. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - g. McDougle, 1926 February 18
      Letter, Baltimore, Md., to Estabrook. Typescript. 1 l.
    - h. Corbin, A. H., 1926 February 23; 1 l.
      Postcard, (Pembroke), N.C. to Estabrook.
    - i. McDougle, Ivan E., 1926 February 23
    - j. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1926 February 23
      Letter, Philadelphia, Pa., to Mr. Corbin. Carbon of typescript. 1 1.
    - k. McDougle, 1926 March 4
    - l. Smith, Jas. W., 1926 March 6
      Letter, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. A. F. Corbin, Pembroke, N.C. Handwritten in ink. 3 l.
    - m. Jacobs, L. W., 1926 March 6
      Letter, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. Brooks (1. i. Estabrook] Handwritten in ink. 3 l.
    - n. Corbin, A. F., 1926 March 9
      Letter, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. Estabrook, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - o. McDougle, 1926 March 16
    - p. (Estabrook?], 1926 March 18
      Letter, to Mr. Corbin. Typescript. 1 l.
    - q. Corbin, A. F., 1926 April 2
      Letter, Pembroke, N.C., to Mr. Estabrook, Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y. Typescript, signed, with handwritten note. 1 l.
    - r. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1926 April 6
    - s. McDougle, 1926 April 22
    - t. McDougle, Ivan E., 1926 June 11
      Letter, Baltimore, 14d., to Estabrook. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
  - 1927, 1.6 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence regarding Studies of Indian Familie), Folder 6)
    - a. Campbell, Olive D., 1927 February 16
      Letter, Brasstown, N.C., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Philadelphia, Pa. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - b. McGibony, J. R., 1946 October 23
      Letter, Washington, D.C., to Mt. A. H. Estabrook, Philadelphia, Pa. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - c. Wolverton, Emma, 1931 December 13
      Letter, Vineland, N.Y. to Dr. Estabrook. Handwritten in ink, signed. 4 p. on 2 l., Christmas card enclosed.
- Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his Studies of Racial Characteristics, 1922; 1924; 1926; Undated; 2
  - The Tribe of Ishmael, 1922; 196 p. (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 8)
    Pages 87 and 93-103 are missing.
  - The Win Tribe. A Study in Triple Racial Mixtures. By Arthur H. Estabrook and Ivan E. McDougle, 1925; 108 p. (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 9)
  - The Win Tribe. The Isshies. - Virginia. A Study in Triple Racial Mixtures. By Arthur H. Estabrook and Ivan E. McDougle, 1926; 133 p. (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 10)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted.
  - The Indian Johns, p. 17-74, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 11)
  - "Triple Crosses", 2.5 (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 12)
    - a. "Triple Crosses in the South: Indian - Negro - White". Abstract, 06/14/1924; 2 l
    - b. "Triple Crosses in the South". May 1, 1925; 5 p.
    - c. "Triple Crosses in the South."' (Carbon) May 1, 1925; 5 l
  - Mongrel Virginians, 2.6 (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 13)
    - a., 1926 March 20; 3 l.
    - b., 1926 March 20; 3 l.
  - "Marriage Records" 4 l., Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts by Arthur H. Estabrook regarding his S), Folder 14)
- Manuscripts by Others, 1924-1925; 3
  - Plecker, W. A. "The New Virginia Law 'To Preserve Racial Integrity'", 1924; 3 p. (Box 1 (3-Manuscripts by Others), Folder 15)
    With "Amended Senate Bill 219 as passed by the Senate February 27th, 1924". 3 p.
  - Smith, Elizabeth. "An Analysis of a 'Croatan' Community", [1925]; 10 p. (Box 1 (3-Manuscripts by Others), Folder 16)
- Genealogical Charts, undated; 4
  - Printed genealogical charts, 4.1 (Box 1 (4-Genealogical Charts), Folder 17)
    - a. The Bob-Salva Family
      The Asa Esther Family.
      The Austin Roxanna Family.
      The Aba Betsey Family.
      The Bill B. Brown Family.
      The Al - Elea Brown Family.
      The Andrew Hall Family.
      Must consult archivist before viewing this material.
    - b. The Willett Family
      The Bruno Family.
      The Hamlin Family.
      The Alphonse Brown Family.
      The Carl Geraldine Family.
      The Abraham Johnson Family.
      The Reuben Ross Family.
      The Saul Lillie Family.
      Abigail's Family.
    - c. The Oswald Family
      The Rupert Brown Family.
      The Amelia Family.
      The Hal - Ada Jones Family.
      The Webster Burton Family.
      The Half-Breed Jones Line.
      The Gus Family.
      The Alta - Sam Long Family.
      The White Brown Family.
      The Half-Breed Brown Family.
      Early Generations of the Wins.
  - Handwritten genealogical charts (Box 1 (4-Genealogical Charts), Folder 18)
    a. Duff.
    b. Early Genealogy of the Isshies.
    c. Amherst, Va. Early notes.
    d. Johns (Deed Book E 111).
    e. [?] (Deed Book DD 334-340).
    f. [Johns - Branham].
    g. Willis.
  - Large genealogical charts - Amherst work sheets (Box 1 (4-Genealogical Charts), Folder 19)
- Notes, 1908-1925; Undated; 5
  - "The Nams", 1912 (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 1)
    Handwritten notes, charts, list of names, and "Key Index to Places in Guilder Hollow Pedigree".
  - "The Nams", 1912 (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 2)
    Preservation photocopy of handwritten notes, charts, list of names, and "Key Index to Places in Guilder Hollow Pedigree".
  - "The Juke Data", 1914 August 1; approximately 88 p. (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 3)
  - Interviews (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 4)
    a. Coleman, Silas.
    b. Dickinson, Sallie P.
    c. Gray, Arthur.
    d. Lewis, Thomas.
    e. Packard, Cornelia.
    f. Packard Cornelia, and Spencer, Miss.
    g. Poole, Mr. J. R.
    h. Sandidge, Dr. and Mrs.
    i. Shields, Mr. A. T.
    j. Whitmell.
  - Notes on the history of the area (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 5)
    a. "Georgia founded...".
    b. "Charlottesville data - 3-11-1411.
    c. "Land Grant Records - Richmond, Va., 1924".
  - Notes on persons (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 6)
    a. "List of children already examined at Amherst Mission".
    b. "Deaths - Amherst"; "Tuberculosis".
    c. [Notes on individuals] 2-7-23.
    d. "Incomplete list 2/20/24".
    e. [Notes. undated].
    f. [Notes on Johns Family, map showing location of known Johns and Branhams of early days].
    g. "The Lowrie History".
    h. "Croatans - 4-1-1925".
    i. "The Wins - Isshies" - Keys to Surnames, places; Other mixed areas; Christian names - Women; Christian names - Men.
    j. "Pictures - Persons, Bldgs., etc".
  - Notes from official records (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 7)
    a. Amherst Co. Records: Criminal Records, Chancery book, Marriage bonds.
    b. Handbook of American Indians North of Mexico.
    c. McMillan, Hamilton. Sir Walter Raleigh's Lost Colony.
    d. Psychological Review, vol. 29, 1922, p. 221.
    e. Surface, G. T. "Racial and Regional Study of the Virginia Population".
    f. (U.S. Census?] - "1908 on census: List of Isshy Area, Miss Packard's notes".
    g. "U.S. Census Estimate of Indians in Virginia, 1920".
    h. "Miscegenation - Virginia".
    i. "Virginia - Race - Legal Definition - History".
    j. Virginia code "1/16th or more negro...".
    k. Miscellaneous: "Registrations in Marriage Licenses", "Virginia Indians", "Re Amherst Indians", 'Washington Library".
  - Information on the project (Box 2 (5-Notes), Folder 8)
    a. "Indian - Negro - White Group, Amherst, Va". 2-1-1923.
    b. "Names of field workers on survey" May 1, 1923.
    c. (Notes on topics to include, records to be checked, etc.].
    d. [Notecards].
- Photographs, 1923-1925; 1931; Undated; 6
  - [Photographs mounted on sheets: Virginia, Amherst County The Isshies; North Carolina, Robeson Co. Triple Mixtures; North Carolina; South Carolina] (Box 2 (6-Photographs), Folder 9)
  - [Album: Photos of Jukes, etc.] (Box 2 (6-Photographs), Folder 10)
  - [Photographs laid in Dugdale, The Jukes] (Box 2 (6-Photographs), Folder 11)
  - [Photographs laid in Campbell The Southern Highlander] (Box 2 (6-Photographs), Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous prints and photographs (Box 2 (6-Photographs), Folder 13)
    a. Emma December 25, 1931.
    b. Negative and positive prints of two pages from an unidentified album (photographs were labeled).
- Clippings, 1912-1936; Undated; 7
  - 1922-1924, 7.1 (Box 2 (7-Clippings), Folder 14)
    - a. Garth, T. R. "The Intelligence of Indians".Science v. 61, no. 1457. 635-36, 1922 December 1
    - b. "Human Dregs"Bulletin, 1923 February 26
    - c. "Virginia Tribe Proves Hard to Classify", from Tribune, 1923 August
    - d.The Pembroke Herald, v. 1, no. 7: 1-6, 1924 March
    - e. First Indian County Commencement At Pembroke So Big It Is Day to Reckon From".The Robesonian v. 60, no. 15 1+, 1924 March 31
    - f. "Set Store by Their Schools", [April? 1924]
    - g. "Studies are being made of Indian psychology..."Science, 05/16/1924
    - h. Seawell, Joseph Lacy. "Black Teacher of Southern Whites".The New York Times Magazine: 8, 1924 May 18